<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
        <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
        <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
        <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
        <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" category="std" version="3" docName="draft-misell-quic-bdp-token-latest">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="QUIC BDP Tokens">QUIC Bandwidth Delay Product Tokens</title>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" status="standard" value="draft-misell-quic-bdp-token-latest"/>
        <author fullname="Q Misell" initials="Q" surname="Misell">
            <organization abbrev="AS207960">AS207960 Cyfyngedig</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>13 Pen-y-lan Terrace</street>
                    <city>Caerdydd</city>
                    <code>CF23 9EU</code>
                    <country>United Kingdom</country>
                </postal>
                <email>q@as207970.net</email>
                <email>q@magicalcodewit.ch</email>
                <uri>https://magicalcodewit.ch</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <area>tsv</area>
        <workgroup>QUIC</workgroup>
        <abstract>
            <t>This document describes a method to store previously calculated Congestion Control parameters on a QUIC
                client to allow additional capacity on high Bandwidth Delay Product paths to be used with
                Careful Resume.</t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section>
            <name>Introduction</name>
            <t>This document describes a method for a QUIC server to send calculated Congestion Control parameters
                to a client for storage and later use on a future connection with Careful Resume
                <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-careful-resume"/>. It also allows the client to inspect CC parameters,
                and allows the client not use them with new connections if its aware of a significant change in the
                BDP of the path.</t>

            <section>
                <name>Requirements Language</name>
                <t>The key words <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>, <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>, <bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>, <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>,
                    <bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>, <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>, <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>, <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>,
                    <bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>, <bcp14>MAY</bcp14>, and <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> in this document are to be
                    interpreted as described in <xref target="BCP14"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals,
                    as shown here.</t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <name>BDP Tokens</name>
            <t>The address validation token is overloaded to also store CC information. This has the advantage that a
                QUIC client unaware of this document will still be able to make use of this specification without
                modification. QUIC<xref target="RFC9000"/> defines an address validation token as an opaque blob that
                the client should not inspect. This document extends this by providing some structure token, whilst
                still providing fields for server specific information.</t>
            <t>The format of a token containing BDP information is defined as follows:</t>
            <figure align="left" suppress-title="false">
                <name>BDP Token</name>
                <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt="">
                    BDP Token {
                        Address Validation Length (i),
                        Address Validation (..),
                        BDP Data Length (i),
                        BDP Data Value(..),
                        Saved Capacity (i),
                        Saved RTT (i)
                    }
                </artwork>
            </figure>
            <t>The fields are as follows:</t>
            <dl>
                <dt>Address Validation Length</dt>
                <dd>
                    A variable-length integer specifying the length of the Address Validation field, in bytes.
                    A value of 0 indicates that the server is not using address validation and is using the token purely
                    for CC information.
                </dd>
                <dt>Address Validation</dt>
                <dd>
                    Opaque information specific to the server that it will use for address validation.
                    The construction of this field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> comply with the requirements of
                    <xref target="RFC9000"/> section 8.1.
                </dd>
                <dt>CC Data Length</dt>
                <dd>
                    A variable-length integer specifying the length of the CC Data field, in bytes.
                    A value of 0 indicates that the server is not using CC Data, and that the Saved Capacity and
                    Saved RTT fields should also be ignored.
                </dd>
                <dt>CC Data</dt>
                <dd>
                    Opaque information specific to the server that it will use to prime its congestion controller state.
                    This field <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> contain expiration/lifetime information, and any additional
                    information that the server may need to validate that the same path is being used, such as an
                    endpoint token defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-careful-resume"/>.
                    The data <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be signed, or otherwise processed against modification by the client.
                </dd>
                <dt>Capacity</dt>
                <dd>
                    The estimated capacity of the path in bytes, encoded as a variable-length integer.
                    The exact CC state value used is left to server preference.
                </dd>
                <dt>RTT</dt>
                <dd>
                    The RTT of the path in microseconds, encoded as a variable-length integer.
                    The exact CC state value used is left to server preference.
                </dd>
            </dl>
            <t>The Capacity and RTT fields are merely hints to the client and the server
                <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> not use these fields when priming its congestion controller state. If it wishes
                to use these parameters it will have to also include them in its CC Data structure, as data in this
                field is protected against modification by the client.</t>
        </section>
        <section>
            <name>Extension signalling</name>
            <t>The server can send the above extended BDP token to all clients without further negotiation. However
                a client needs some way to know that there is meaningful structure to a token its received from the
                server. To this end a new transport parameter is defined.</t>
            <dl>
                <dt>bdp_token (0xTBD)</dt>
                <dd>
                    The bdp_token transport parameter is a boolean value that indicates that the server is using
                    BDP tokens. It can have the following values:
                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t>0, default value: BDP Tokens are not in use.</t>
                        <t>1: BDP Tokens are in use.</t>
                    </list>
                </dd>
            </dl>
        </section>

        <section anchor="IANA">
            <name>IANA Considerations</name>
            <section>
                <name>QUIC Transport Parameters</name>
                <t>Per this document, one new entry has been added to the "QUIC Transport Parameters" registry defined in
                    <xref target="RFC9000"/> section 22.3. This entry is defined below:</t>
                <table>
                    <name>New entries</name>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Value</th>
                            <th>Status</th>
                            <th>Specification</th>
                            <th>Parameter name</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td>0xTBD</td>
                            <td>Provisional</td>
                            <td>This document</td>
                            <td>bdp_frame</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="Security">
            <name>Security Considerations</name>
            <t>The CC Data field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be protected against manipulation by malicious clients.
                A client that can modify CC calculations could otherwise cause overload of the network path.</t>
            <t>The Capacity and RTT fields are hints to the client and not protected from modification by a client. The
                server <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ignore when processing a received BDP token.</t>
        </section>
    </middle>

    <back>
        <references>
            <name>References</name>
            <references>
                <name>Normative References</name>

                <referencegroup anchor="BCP14" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/bcp14">
                    <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
                    <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
                </referencegroup>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.9000.xml"/>
            </references>
            <references>
                <name>Informative References</name>

                <xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/draft-ietf-tsvwg-careful-resume-04.xml"/>
            </references>
        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>
